Finding Aid for Institute for the Humanities (University of Michigan) Records 1988-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Audio-Visual Material
  - Utopian Visions 1992-1993
    - Videotapes
      - Conference: "Utopian Revisions: Nationalism and Civil Society in Eastern Europe" October 29-30, 1992, 6 videotapes
        - Edmund Mokrzycki, Sociology, Polish Academy of Sciences. Conference session: "The Vicious Circle of Utopias in Eastern Europe" (Box 5)
        - Mykola Ryabchuk, senior editor Vsevit, and poet, Kiev. Conference session: "Between Civil Society and the New Etatism: Democracy in the Making and/or the State Building in Ukraine" (Box 5)
        - Andrew Arato, Sociology, New School for Social Research. Conference session: "Revolution, Restoration and Legitimation: Ideological Problems of the Transition from State Socialism" (Box 5)
        - Vitaly Komar, Russian and Alexander Melamid, Russian émigré artists, New York. Conference session: "What Is to Be Done with Monumental Propaganda?" (Box 5)
        - Michael Kennedy, Global Partnership Fellow. Moderator (Box 5)
      - Paula Gunn Allen, English, University of California, Los Angeles. Reading: "A Reading From Her Work" November 10, 1992 (Box 5)
      - Carol Neely, English and Women's Studies, University of Illinois. Forum: "Loss and Restoration in Women's Utopias: Margaret Cavendish's Description of a New World Called the Blazing World" November 6, 1992 (Box 5)
      - Aaron Betsky, Otis Parsons Art Institute. Forum: "Taking the Train to Aleph: Transforming L.A." January 22, 1992 (Box 6)
      - Conference: "The Utopian Body: Medicine, Technology, Ethics" January 30, 1993
        - John Hoberman, Germanic Languages, University of Texas at Austin. Conference session: "The Emergence of the Dynamic-Athletic Body", 7 videotapes (Box 6)
        - Robert A. Aronowitz MD, Internal Medicine, Robert Wood Johnson Medical School. Conference session: "Between Two Utopias: Changing Ideas About Angina Pectoris" (Box 6)
        - David Morris, author The Culture of Pain. Conference session: "Utopian Bodies/Dystopian Minds: Depression, Pain and Disability" (Box 6)
        - Barbara Stafford, Art History, University of Chicago. Conference session: "The Aesthetics of Medical Ethics" (Box 6)
        - Samuel Delany, Comparative Literature, University of Massachusetts. Forum: "The Rhetoric of Sex/The Discourse of Desire" (Box 6)
        - Barbara Stafford, Art History, University of Chicago. Forum: "Visual Evidence: Technological Utopia or 'System of Imposture'?" (Box 6)
        - Charles Hamm, Music, emeritus, Dartmouth. Forum: "Israel Zangwill and Irving Berlin: The Melting-Pot as Utopia" (Box 6)
      - Conference: "Conference on Collaboration" April 23-25, 1993
        - James Winn and Fred Bookstein. Conference session: "The Intellectual Economy of Interdisciplinary Scholarship." Sidra Ezrahi, moderator (Box 6)
        - Carol Neely. Conference session: "In the Borderlands;" Louise Stein. Conference session: "Climbing into the Abyss." Lenard Barkin, moderator (Box 6)
        - Samuel Floyd, Richard Crawford, Timothy Taylor. Conference session: "Food for Thought" and "Forms of Musical Collaboration." Michael Schoenfeldt, moderator (Box 6)
        - Peter Railton. Conference session: Interdisciplinary Multi... and Tom Zuidema. Conference session: The Anthropology of ..." Diane Kirpatrick, moderator (Box 6)
        - Geoff Eley. Conference session: "Freedom from Discipline." June Howard, moderator (Box 6)
        - Conference Wrap-Up (Box 6)
      - Euripides' Bacchae, May 23-24 (Box 6)
    - Cassette Tapes
      - Paula Gunn Allen, English, University of California, Los Angeles. Reading October 10, 1992 (Box 7)
      - Michael Silverstein, Anthropology, University of Chicago. Lecture: "Modern Prophets of Language" October 23, 1992 (Box 7)
      - Conference: "Utopian Revisions: Nationalism and Civil Society in Eastern Europe" October 29-30, 1992, 6 audiocassettes
        - Richard Wagner, writer, Berlin; writer in residence, Oberlin College, 1992-1993. Conference session: "Ethnic Minorities in the National State: The Case of German-Romanians" (Box 7)
        - Konrad Weiss, member, German Bundestag. Conference session: "The Power and Frailty of Utopia" (Box 7)
        - Edmund Mokrzycki, Sociology, Polish Academy of Sciences. Conference session: "The Vicious Circle of Utopias in Eastern Europe" (Box 7)
        - Vladimir Tismaneanu, Government and Politics, University of Maryland. Conference session: "Fantasies of Salvation: Varieties of Nationalism in Post-Communist Eastern Europe" (Box 7)
        - Andrew Arato, Sociology, New School for Research. Conference session: "Revolution, Restoration and Legitimation: Ideological Problems of the Transition from State Socialism" (Box 7)
        - Vitaly Komar and Alexander Melamid, Russian émigré artists. Conference session: "What Is to Be Done with Monumental Propaganda?" (Box 7)
      - Conference: "The Utopian Body: Medicine, Technology, and Ethics" January 30, 1993, 3 audiocassettes
        - Robert A. Aronwitz MD, Internal Medicine, Robert Wood Johnson Medical School. Conference session: "Between Two Utopias: Changing Ideas About Angina Pectoris" (Box 7)
        - John Hoberman, Germanic Languages, University of Texas at Austin. Conference session: "The Emergence of the Dynamic-Athletic Body" (Box 7)
        - David Morris, author The Culture of Pain. Conference session: "Utopian Bodies/Dystopian Minds: Depression, Pain and Disability" (Box 7)
  - The Geography of Identity 1993-1994
    - Videotapes
      - Julie Ellison, English, University of Michigan. Forum: "There and Back: Transatlantic Novels and Anglo-American Careers" September 24, 1993 (Box 7)
      - Anne Stevenson, American/British poet and biographer. Forum: "How You Say the World is What You Get" October 15, 1993 (Box 7)
      - Conference "Remapping Identities: Colonial and Post-Colonial Societies" November 5, 1993, 3 videotapes
        - Billie Melman, History, Tel Aviv University. Conference session: "Transparent Veils: Western Women Dis-Orient the East" (Box 7)
        - Anton Shammas, Comparative Literature, University of Michigan. Conference session: "Autocartography: The Case of Palestine, Michigan" (Box 7)
        - James Winn, Director, Institute for the Humanities. Concluding discussion (Box 7)
      - Rashid Khalidi, Middle East History, University of Chicago. Forum: "Palestinian Identity: National Consciousness without a Nation-State" December 3, 1993 (Box 7)
      - Fred Cooper, History and Residential College, University of Michigan. Forum: "Modernizing Bureaucrats, Backward Africans, and the Development Concept" January 14, 1994 (Box 7)
      - Conference: "Culture, Time and Place" February 4, 1994, 5 videotapes
        - Herman Lebovics, History, SUNY at Stony Brook. Conference session: "How to Preserve a National Cultural Heritage and Kill Off Cultural Creativity." Keith Morrison, San Francisco Art Institute. Conference session: "Culture, Experience and Memory: Global Odyssey of a Caribbean Manchild." (Box 7)
        - Michael Watts, Geography, University of CA, Berkeley. Conference session: "Mapping Identities: Globalization, Territoriality, and the Politics of Place." Pieter Judson, History, Swarthmore College. Conference session: "Frontiers, Islands, Forests, Stones: Mapping a German Identity in the Habsburg Monarchy, 1848-1900" (Box 7)
        - Nuala Ni Dhomhnaill, Poet, Ireland. Jill Harris Memorial Lecture: "Dinnsheanchas: The Naming of High or Holy Places" (Box 7)
        - Saskia Sassen, Urban Planning, Columbia University. Conference session: "Identity in the Global City: Economic and Cultural Encasements" (Box 7)
        - Concluding Discussion (Box 7)
      - Stanley Crouch, author and winner of 1993 MacArthur Fellowship. Forum: "Chasing the Bird: Discovering the Identity of Charlie Parker" March 4, 1994 (Box 7)
        (cosponsored by the School of Music)
      - Arjun Appadurai. Forum: "Sovereignty Without Territoriality: Notes for a Postnational Geography" April 8, 1994 (Box 7)
    - Cassette Tapes
      - Conference: "Remapping Identities: Colonial and Post-Colonial Societies" November 5, 1994, 5 audiocassettes
        - Billie Melman, History, Tel Aviv University. Conference session: "Transparent Veils: Western Women Dis-Orient the East" (Box 8)
        - Anton Shammas, Comparative Literature, University of Michigan. Conference session: "Autocartography: The Case of Palestine, Michigan" (Box 8)
        - Frederick Cooper, History and Residential College, University of Michigan. Conference session: "The Dialectics of Decolonization: Nationalism and Labor Movements in Post-War Africa" (Box 8)
        - Judith Becker, Ethnomusicology, University of Michigan. "A New Frame for an Old Javanese Dance" (Box 8)
        - James Winn, Director, Institute for the Humanities. Concluding discussion (Box 8)
      - Conference: "Culture, Time and Place" February 4-5, 1994, 5 videotapes
        - Herman Lebovics, History, SUNY at Stony Brook. Conference session: "How to Preserve a National Cultural Heritage and Kill Off Cultural Creativity." Keith Morrison, San Francisco Art Institute. Conference session: "Culture, Experience and Memory: Global Odyssey of a Caribbean Manchild." (Box 8)
        - Michael Watts, Geography, University of CA, Berkeley. Conference session: "Mapping Identities: Globalization, Territoriality, and the Politics of Place." Pieter Judson, History, Swarthmore College. Conference session: "Frontiers, Islands, Forests, Stones: Mapping a German Identity in the Habsburg Monarchy, 1848-1900" (Box 8)
        - Nuala Ni Dhomhnaill, Poet, Ireland. Jill Harris Memorial Lecture: "Dinnsheanchas: "The Naming of High or Holy Places" (Box 8)
        - Saskia Sassen, Urban Planning, Columbia University. Conference session: "Identity in the Global City: Economic and Cultural Encasements." Gwendolyn Wright, Architecture, Columbia University. Conference session: "Pragmatic Modernism: American Visions of the City Between the Wars" (Box 8)
        - Concluding Discussion (Box 8)
        - Laura Downs, Summary (Box 8)
      - March 11
        - Stanley Crouch, author of Notes of a Hanging Judge and winner of a 1993 MacArthur Fellowship. Forum: Sciences and the Humanities Seminar: "The Problem with the Skin Game" (Box 8)
      - Stanley Crouch, WUOM Interview March 18, 1994 (Box 8)
      - James Winn, director, Institute for the Humanities. Brown Bag: "Geography, Economy and the Arts: A Report on the Salzburg Seminar" February 8, 1994 (Box 8)
  - Work and Play 1994-1995
    - Videotape
      - Richard Lanham, English, University of California, Los Angeles. Illustrated Lecture: "From Book to Screen: An Introduction to Multimedia Text" September 21, 1994 (Box 8)
        (cosponsored by the School of Information and Library Studies)
      - Richard Lanham, English, University of California, Los Angeles. Forum: "The New Economics of Human Attention" September 30, 1994 (Box 8)
      - Nancy Van Deusen, Musicology, Claremont Graduate School. Forum: "Between Sophistication and the Spoof: Charivari in the Middle Ages" November 4, 1994 (Box 8)
      - Ted Cohen, Philosophy, University of Chicago. Forum: "Notes on the Aesthetic Structure of Ball Games" January 13, 1995 (Box 8)
      - Anthony Grafton, History, Princeton University. Lecture: "Obelisks and Horoscopes: Astrology and Astral Religion in Renaissance Europe" January 24, 1995 (Box 8)
      - Conference: "Serious Play, Playful Work" February 10-11, 1994, 5 videotapes
        - Carlin A. Barton, History, University of Massachusetts. Conference session: "Playing with Fire: The Contest in Ancient Rome" (Box 8)
        - Richard Lim, History, Smith College. Conference session: "The Origins of Sunday as a Public Holiday in Late Antiquity" (Box 8)
        - Jean L. Briggs. Anthropology, Memorial University of Newfoundland. Conference session: "Out of the Garden of Eden: Morality Play in the Life an Inuit 3 year old." Kathy Peiss, History, University of Massachusetts. Conference session: "At Work on the Play of Appearance: 'Modern Women's' Account of Making Up" (Box 8)
        - Gail Holst-Warhaft, Society for the Humanities, Cornell University. Conference session: "The Fun in the Funeral: Play and the Work of Mourning." Michael Fishbane, Jewish Studies, University of Chicago Divinity School. Conference session: "To Jump for Joy: The Rites of Dance in Bratzlav Hasidism" (Box 8)
        - Summary Panel Discussion (Box 8)
      - David Scobey, American Culture and History, University of Michigan. Forum: "Nymphs and Satyrs: Sex and the Bourgeois Sphere in Victorian New York" March 24, 1995 (Box 8)
      - Symposium: Vitaly Komar and Alexander Melamid, Russian émigré artists; Jim Cogswell, Art, University of Michigan; Michael Kennedy, Sociology/Russian and East European Studies, University of Michigan and Marina Mangubi, Art, Salem State College, Massachusetts. April 12, 1995 (Box 8)
        (cosponsored by the Museum of Art and the School of Art)
      - Adrian Rifkin, Fine Arts, University of Leeds. Forum: "The Epistemology of the Locker Room: Some Kantian Thoughts on the Pornographic Sublime" April 13, 1995 (Box 8)
    - Cassette Tapes
      - Richard Lanham, English, University of California, Los Angeles. WUOM Interview September 27, 1994 (Box 8)
      - Jeffrey T. Schnapp, Italian and Comparative Literature, Stanford University. Lecture: "Border Crossings: Italian/German Peregrinations of the Theater of Totality" January 19, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Emotions 1995-1996
    - Videotapes
      - Susan McClary, Musicology, UCLA. Forum: "Second Hand Emotions: Constructions of Interiority in Music" September 8, 1995 (Box 8)
      - Sabine MacCormack, History and Classical Studies, University of Michigan. Forum: "The Tears Run down in Vain: Vergil and Augustine of Hippo" October 20, 1995 (Box 8)
      - Conference: "Emotion in the Public Sphere" November 3, 1995, 3 videotapes
        - David Burge, Pianist, composer, author, San Diego. Conference session: "The Condition of Music." Ann Cvetkovich, English, University of Texas, Austin. Conference session: "Lesbian Passions and Public Emotions." Respondents: Andrew Mead, Music theory, and Julie Ellison, English, University of Michigan (Box 9)
        - Peter Stearns, Dean of the College of Humanities and Social Sciences and Heinz Professor of History, Carnegie Mellon University. Conference session: "Emotional Change and Political Disengagement in the 20th Century United States." Respondent: Don Herzog, Political Science and Law, University of Michigan (Box 9)
        - Michael Krausz, Philosophy, Bryn Mawr. Conference session: "Changing One's Mind, Changing One's Emotions." Respondent: Stephen Darwall, Philosophy, University of Michigan. Also: Concluding discussion (Box 9)
      - Anna Wierzbicka, Linguistics, Australian National University. Forum: "Emotions Across Cultures -- Diversity and Universality" November 9, 1995 (Box 9)
      - Lila Abu-Lughod, Anthropology, New York University. Forum: "Melodrama and Modernity: The Politics of Morality, the Production of the Subject, and the Egyptian Television Serial" December 1, 1995 (Box 9)
      - Robin D.G. Kelly. Forum: "Playing for Keeps" December 9, 1995 (Box 9)
      - Conference: "Unruly Emotions, Disorderly Conduct" February 8-9, 1996, 5 videotapes
        - Taslima Nasrin, poet, novelist, human/women's rights advocate, Bangladesh. Conference session: "I Make Most of My Emotions Public" (Box 9)
        - Michael Daugherty, School of Music, University of Michigan. Conference session: "Jackie O'pera: A Preview with Librettist Wayne Koestenbaum" (Box 9)
        - Michael Rogin, Political Science, University of California at Berkeley. Conference session: "What Is Race?" (Box 9)
        - Wayne Koestenbaum, English, Yale University. Conference session: "There Is No Penny and No Slot" (Box 9)
        - Laura Engelstein, History, Princeton University. Conference session: "Ecstasy, Anxiety, and the Erotics of Fear: Castration Tales in Tsarist Russia" (Box 9)
  - Images and the Imaginary 1996-1997
    - Videotapes
      - Vladimir Obatnin. Artist, Hermitage Group, St. Petersburg, Russia. Lecture: "The History of the Hermitage Group" October 18, 1996 (Box 9)
      - Conference: "Representation and Images" November 9, 1996
        - Stephen Easter, Biology, University of Michigan. Conference session: "The Representation and Analysis of Images in the Brain" (Box 9)
        - Andrew Mead, Music Theory and Composition, University of Michigan. Conference session: "Bodily Hearing: Physiological Metaphors and Musical Understanding" (Box 9)
        - Philip Hanlon, Mathematics, University of Michigan. Conference session: "Why Does Geometry Have to Be So Mathematical?" (Box 9)
        - Mame Jackson, Art History, Wayne State University. Conference session: "Where 'Sleeps' are a Measure of Miles -- Concepts of Space and Time in Inuit Art" (Box 9)
      - Simon Goldhill, Classics, King's College, Cambridge. Forum: "The Erotic Eye: Stimulating Images and Competing Cultures of Viewing" December 6, 1996 (Box 9)
      - Kathleen Woodward, Center for Twentieth-Century Studies, University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee. Forum: "Shifting Shame: From Sarte and Toni Morrison to Mass Culture" March 15, 1997 (Box 9)
      - Victor Nell, Psychology, University of South Africa. Forum: "Bad Values, Evil Emotions" March 29, 1997 (Box 9)
      - Pauline Yu, East Asian Languages and Cultures, University of California, Los Angeles. Forum: "Charting the Landscape of Chinese Poetry" January 7, 1997 (Box 9)
      - Symposium: "Ideals of Appearance" February 20-21, 1997, 5 videotapes
        - Patricia Simons, Art History and Women's Studies, University of Michigan, moderator. Martin Pernick, History, University of Michigan. Symposium session: "Beauty and Disease" (Box 10)
        - Fred Bookstein, Human Growth and Development, University of Michigan. Symposium session: "Geometry and Facial Beauty: A Biometric Meditation" (Box 10)
        - Claire Prussian, artist. Symposium session: "My Art, My Self" (Box 10)
        - Joel Howell, Internal Medicine, History, Public Health, University of Michigan. Symposium session: "Public Perceptions of the X-Ray Image: Meaning, Gender and Power, 1895-1925" (Box 10)
        - Sharon Patton, Center for African American Studies, Art History, University of Michigan. Symposium session: "Changing the Subject." Also, Panel discussion (Box 10)
      - Froma Zeitlin, Classics, Princeton. Forum: "A Passion for Viewing" March 21, 1997 (Box 10)
      - Symposium: "Transgression, Graffiti and Cultural Projection of the Image" [Regulation of the Image] April 7, 1997, 5 videotapes
        - Evelyn Velez-Aguayo, Dance, University of Michigan. Symposium session: "Embodied Memories of Evelina, Ampelina: An Autobiographical Lens of Dance and Language" (Box 10)
        - Joseph Grigely, School of Art and Design, University of Michigan. Symposium session: "Editing Bodies" (Box 10)
        - Coralynn Davis, Anthropology, University of Michigan. Symposium session: "Developing sisters: Maithil Craft Producers and the Construction of Feminist Identity Through Tourist Art." Erika Wolf, History of Art, University of Michigan. Symposium session: "Modernism's Willing Executioners: Soviet Avant-Garde Propaganda for the Stalinist Regime" (Box 10)
        - Kristina Milnor, Classics, University of Michigan. Symposium session: "Art/Girl: Graffiti, Femininity, and the Career of Lady Pink" (Box 10)
        - N. Frank Ukadike, Communications, Film and Video, University of Michigan. Symposium session: "Video Booms and the Manifestations of First Cinema in Anglophone Africa" (Box 10)
  - Narrative 1997-1998
    - Videotapes
      - Kimberly Camp, Museum of African American History, Detroit, President. "Embodying the Narrative of African American History" February 20, 1998 (Box 10)
  - Form and Pattern 1998-1999
    - Cassette Tapes
      - Symposium: "Trauma, Silence and Survival" March 19-20, 1999, 9 audiocassettes
        - Opening Reception. "Relive the Magic: An Evening with Tony Amore" Performed by writer-composer Andrew Kirshner, Music, University of Michigan (Box 10)
        - Carol Bier, Curator, Textile Museum, Washington D.C. Symposium session: "Between Metaphysics and Revelation" (Box 10)
        - Marion Guck, School of Music, University of Michigan. Symposium session: "Patterns of Musical Pacing" (Box 10)
        - Bill Jacobson, photographer, New York. Symposium session: "Images of Loss, Vehicles of Remembrance" (Box 10)
        - Israel Liberzon, Psychiatry, University of Michigan. Symposium session: "Functional Neuroimaging of Traumatic Experience" (Box 10)
        - Cathy Caruth, Emory University. Symposium session: "Trauma, Silence, and Survival" (Box 10)
        - Sumathi Ramaswamy, History, University of Michigan. Symposium session: "Cartography, Nationalism, and the Politics of Deity in Modern India" (Box 10)
        - Jennifer Trimble, Classical Art and Archaeology, University of Michigan. Symposium session: "Female Bodies, Religious Practice and the Power of Local Elites in the Roman Empire" (Box 10)
        - Roger Friedland, University of California at Santa Barbara. Symposium session: "The Sex of State: The Political Morphology of Religious Nationalism" (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Videotapes
      - Kennedy Center Honors, Roger L. Stevens December 1988 (Box 10)
      - Meredith Harris discussion with James Winn. "Why I Give to the Humanities Institute and the University of Michigan" May 17, 1992 (Box 10)
      - Farewell reception for James Winn at Art Museum April 21, 1995 (Box 10)
      - Riprap #2: Tom Trautman, Director, Institute for the Humanities 1998 (Box 10)
      - Javanese Dance Undated (Box 10)
      - Peter Sparling, Dance, University of Michigan Undated, 2 videotapes (Box 10)
      - Simon Schama, Historian, Harvard University circa 1989-1990 (Box 10)